[Music]
do
hello good evening everybody good
evening good day to all of you welcome
to a new episode of ask abidjit i hope
you are doing well
and let's see who all is there with us
today tonight
i can see
cherry karthik twilight tejus vampire
devyang swam
crazy brain sciam tanish crawl wind
foodie travelers home sharma
adidev and lots of other people good
evening good day to all of you great to
be with you all again
and as always we have a whole bunch of
questions that i have selected and
hopefully i will answer many of them
and if we have some time at the end
we're gonna take some live chat
questions as well from the live chat
so let me begin with the uh
questions that i have
picked let's begin with question number
one
ranjit nayak says what is the perfect
time to declare a war what's the perfect
time to declare war the perfect time to
declare a war is when you know that you
cannot lose
that is the right time to declare a war
if you are strong enough
that you will not lose and
and if you know the enemy's capabilities
and you have made a proper judgment
assessment of where you stand and where
the enemy stands and when you are
confident
that you cannot lose the war that is the
perfect time to declare a war you cannot
get into a war in which you have a
significant chance of losing you simply
can't do that you should not do that
so the perfect time to declare a war is
when you are
impregnable when your position is in
technical prep
when your position is
impregnable and even you simply cannot
lose when you have covered all the bases
and you have made sure that all your
defenses are
perfect
that's when you can go into a war
because you simply can't lose and that
would give you a significant chance of
winning
so that is the perfect time to declare a
war
mohammed danish khan says india pakistan
pakistan afghanistan israel palestine
sri lanka sinali tamils and china hong
kong are all of the mentioned countries
that have disputes with one another in
some way or the other
while the british are living their life
away from all the chaos they created was
this done unintentionally
or was this a well thought out plot
the british did not do any of this
unintentionally they created problems
wherever they went
whichever countries they colonized or
occupied or fought against they created
divisions within those countries
within those societies exploited those
divisions in order to rule them
and then when they left they created
bigger problems before the left
that is the
good old cliche of divide and conquer
divide and rule that's what the british
have done everywhere
whether it's in africa whether it's in
asia whether it's
anywhere else whether it's in the
british islands themselves
they have always used the strategy of
divide and rule
there are so many civil wars going on in
africa because of the british policy of
divide and rule
and even in the british isles themselves
there is this policy that you can see of
dividend rule let me show you an example
let's go to the map
as you guys know
as you all know i am very fond of the
map so let's take a look at the british
islands
take a look at
what's
west of the united kingdom
we have
ireland which is one single island
and yet this one single island ireland
is divided politically into northern
ireland
and southern ireland
southern ireland is more or less an
independent country
well de facto independent
but northern ireland is occupied by the
uk by britain
right
and as you can see this is a divided
island a divided country the same people
it is the same people but they are
divided who divided them it's the uk
it's the british it's the english who
divided them so the capital of northern
ireland is belfast and the capital of
southern ireland is dublin
so that's how it is so even in ireland
they use the policy of divide and rule
even in ireland they had this policy of
creating artificial famines
read it up look it up the great potato
famine and whatnot
so they they did these things even in
ireland and lots of other places
and the americans have continued the
policy in some ways let's take a look at
the korean peninsula north korea south
korea
i mean it's not exactly like
they intended to do this but well that's
how it is north korea south korea in
india they divided the fragmented the
great subcontinent into a bunch of
nations nation states pakistan
afghanistan nepal
uh bangladesh sri lanka maldives
one could even argue that myanmar would
have been part of the indian
subcontinent indian civilization anyway
so that's what they did here in india
and africa is as we have discussed many
times full of these strange straight
lines on the map
arbitrary straight lines that the
european powers have
drawn up
and
arbitrary nations they have created many
of these have been created by the uk by
the british
so this is a policy they have used time
and time again
to create trouble to create problems to
set fire
to places to countries to cultures
societies all around the world that's
what they've done again and again and
again and it's
and
many of the problems that you see in the
world today
are a legacy of what these people left
behind what the british left behind
so this so none of this was
unintentional they have created these
problems everywhere they went
uh whether it's in india whether it's or
whether it's the
sinali's tamil
issue
whether it is israel palestine even
there there's a there's a deep history
of what these people did
the entirety of the middle east even in
the middle east you will see these
straight lines on the map
yes shall we take a look
as you can see
the straight lines once again
all of these
artificial nations were created by the
western powers mostly it was the british
who did this
look up the history
the arabian peninsula is now
saudi arabia what does saudi arabia mean
it means that it's arabia ruled by the
house of saud who are the saudis who who
what is the house of saud it's a dynasty
a family that was
installed
by the british
more or less
look up the history
so they have done this wherever they
went
divide and rule divide and conquer
and uh
so the british are enjoying the fruits
of these of all of this labor that they
have
done over the past couple of hundred
years
yes and they have become immensely rich
as a consequence of what they have done
and all of these puppet regimes and and
artificial states they left behind and
created they are in many ways behold to
the british beholden to the british and
much of the world's illicit wealth
has found its way into london
and
such other places
so all of this was not unintentional it
was all very well thought out
and the same policy continues today by
the success
the successor state
of the british empire
so
that's what we see today none of this is
under unintentional all of it was done
on purpose
all right harshit
says
you have said in one of your sessions
that our country or civilization has
always been fully industrialized and
urbanized
but at the same time we always
maintained a balance and equilibrium
with nature our inventions and
technology never harmed the environment
and surroundings in any way
unlike today we are running out of
resources and destroying our planet that
we have to rush in search of other
planets for our new habitat
i'm curious to know what kind of
industrialization was that
and does it have any relevance in
today's world and can we revive the
system again so that we don't destroy
our planet for resources
um okay the question was asked by
somebody else but yeah all right
so
industrialization doesn't necessarily
destroy the planet
i mean as we know india was a completely
fully urbanized and industrialized
society
five thousand six thousand years before
today we know that we have the evidence
the archaeological evidence the largest
ancient civilization in terms of
geographical area
the saraswati hindu phase of india's
civilization and also fully urbanized
extraordinarily technologically
developed and so on and so forth so
there was complete industrialization and
yet there was no destruction of the
environment none whatsoever so what was
different then and what is when what's
happened what's gone wrong today
right that's the question
it's very simple
those days
you had industries that manufactured all
kinds of goods and items and things like
that but
they manufactured things that lasted
all right
so let's say
you want to manufacture let's say pots
you manufacture pots that will last a
thousand years maybe 5000 years we still
find fragments of those spots some of
them are intact
right
and if you manufacture boats or ships
you manufacture boats or ships that will
last a long time 50 years 100 years
maybe
whatever you manufacture you manufacture
it to last
that's how it was in our civilization
when it was at its peak
we did not
treat the environment as a disposable
resource
today what's happening
is we are treating the environment as a
commodity as a disposable commodity a
disposable resource we are
plundering the earth for minerals and
what not and what is all of this
mineral wealth and resource wealth being
used for for disposable commodities
what's happened is that capitalism has
ruined the world it is in the process of
ruining reading the world
the english-speaking people wherever
they went
they saw whatever land they conquered as
as conquered territory it doesn't belong
to it's it's not our territory it's
something we have acquired conquered so
we can use it plunder it
and ruin it it's perfectly fine that's
what they have done to north america
that's what they did in various other
places
that's what they did in india
they
wiped out india's forests they wiped out
the wildlife of india the cheetahs
they
polluted india's sacred rivers india is
a river valley civilization all rivers
were sacred and today what you find is
the legacy of the british empire that
indian the the modern indian state dumps
sewage
into the rivers
well this was started by the british and
after the so-called independence we just
continued the same policies
so that's one thing the other thing is
capitalism the the
whatever is created today
is supposed to be disposable you buy a
tv a big wide screen lcd led whatever tv
you buy
it's gonna last two or three years then
it's gonna stop working
in the past maybe 50 years before today
if you bought a tv it would last 50
years
if someone bought a tv in the 1980s i am
sure that tv tv would still work today
right if you bought a refrigerator in
the 1970s that refrigerator that fridge
would still be working
but if you buy an expensive fridge today
it will be you'll be lucky if it lasts
five years if it works for five years
you buy an air conditioner today it will
last two or three years if you had
bought one 20 years ago it would still
work
so what's happened is that
the policy is today such that whatever
you manufacture you ensure it doesn't
last long so customers have to keep
buying the same product over and over
again and that's how your your company
grows that's why you have that's how you
uh you attain this quarter upon quarter
profit this never ending growth
on a finite planet so you want infinite
never-ending growth on a finite planet
with finite resources what's going to
happen the planet is going to get ruined
we are ruining the environment we are
running our soil we are ruining the
forest we are ruining our ecosystem we
are reading the oceans we are dumping
plastic into the oceans we are polluting
the atmosphere
all of that is being done
because of this
this uh
quest for never-ending infinite growth
on a finer planet
so in
india when india was fully urbanized
industrialized
we manufactured things that would last a
very long time
what we
sought
was not never ending growth
we built things to last
and we exported things that uh to other
other cultures etc like spices etc in a
way that was sustainable
and as a result india became incredibly
wealthy
so that is the difference
in in the
in the 21st century even in the 20th
century we have had this rise of
capitalism which is essentially
stripping the planet for resources
and what it does is is it concentrates
wealth in the hands of a very few people
it creates this incredible disparity of
income and and wealth and power and
everything and it destroys the planet
now
i am not
pro-socialism
or pro-marxism or whatever but
capitalism clearly is not the right
answer
because it's destroying the planet so
maybe we need to think about what india
did right all these thousands of years
ago india became fully industrialized a
highly technologically developed society
and civilization
and it was done in a very sustainable
way so the growth was not
staggeringly fast
today what happens is that within a
decade you have a new company that comes
up and becomes a
100 billion dollar company
that sort of growth is simply not
possible when you're not destroying the
planet
so in india the growth happened slowly
over centuries over thousands of years
and over time india became a massively
prosperous and wealthy civilization it
did not happen overnight it was the
result of of generations
of work
of the work put in by generations of
indians
right so there was slow growth but it
was sustainable growth you simply cannot
achieve that sort of growth in 10 years
or 20 years or even
50 years takes time so that's what india
did we did not destroy the environment
we did not plunder the environment we
did not look upon the environment as a
disposable resource something that is
for us to enjoy
right
so so that's the difference
that's why the the planet is being
destroyed today it is
capitalism it is mercantilism it is
uh this world view of looking everything
as a resource looking at everything as a
resource to be exploited
so that is not the indian way of doing
things but it is the western way of
doing things
maybe you could say it's the abrahamic
way of doing things because that's what
they say in their holy books
enjoy whatever the the whatever god has
given you
enjoy the fish enjoy the oceans enjoy
whatever right
so that's a very different world view
from what
india has always had and that's why the
planet is being destroyed
and of course they would now like to
blame india and china and other
developing countries for what's
happening for what they have done over
the past 2 300 years
all the pollution
all the destruction of the planet
whatever whatever climate change we are
seeing today is the consequence of the
past two three hundred years of
destruction
wrought by the west
and now they're trying to blame the
developing countries for that please
don't develop because you are destroying
the planet further come on man
so that's that's the answer in brief
rama lakshmi says recently many reports
of usage of dolphins by russia for
military purposes but these have been
known since decades they have been using
do you think we need to use animals in a
way to fulfill purposes and we have been
seeing decrease in wildlife and cattle
increasing
should there be more petting of these
wild animals as people just pet them
based on looks it's a moral question
okay when it comes to the usage of
dolphins and other things uh other such
animals in the
for military purposes well like you say
it's been it's been done for decades
it's been it's been going on for years
the americans have been using training
dolphins for various military activities
not only dolphins even orcas you know
the killer whales pilot whales and so on
so um
that's that's something they've been
doing for years they've been using seals
for such purposes even octopuses for
such purposes and various other animals
and forget about these animals they have
been even doing
such things such experiments on human
beings on hapless unknowing humans
that's what they have been doing so
that's what these people have been doing
for a very long time
for the best part of the past century or
so
so is it a good thing should we use
animals like that no we should not it's
it's like you're saying it's a like you
say it's a moral question it's an
ethical it's a question of ethics
the western abrahamic worldview is that
animals are resources to be exploited
and they don't see animals as sentient
beings and even if they're sentient
they're not humans it's okay let them
suffer let them pay the price of
whatever we want them to do
so that's how they have always looked
upon animals as a resource
and you know how it is right in the west
i mean the animal agriculture it's it's
industrialized it's on it's on a massive
scale
they are
they kill millions maybe maybe billions
of animals every year for
for the purpose of
raising meat
and much of this meat is just wasted you
kill these hundreds of millions of
animals and you waste a significant
portion of that meat that you uh
extracted out of these out of these
beings
through a great deal of pain and misery
so uh
and and animal agriculture is
extraordinarily destructive to the
planet
i mean
in in the us i think the us is the
world's largest consumer of beef
they raise millions maybe hundreds of
millions of cattle every year maybe
billions of chickens and god knows what
else right
and
to feed all of these cows that they are
raising for meat you need i mean
the amount of uh
water
it takes
to to create one pound of beef is like
enough to
uh water
multiple football field size of
something like that you know there is
this very interesting movie called
cowspiracy
i would highly recommend you guys all
ladies gents all of you watch that movie
it gives you the exact statistics i
don't have the figures in the of the top
of my head right head right now but it
takes a shocking amount of water to
create just one pound of beef
and not only that this animal
agriculture it it causes deforestation
and why is that because to feed all of
these animals
you need to grow
plants mostly it's soybeans they're
raising so so you need to
have massive amounts of soybean fields
and then you extract the soybeans out of
that and then you feed the cows so that
they grow
they grow large because soybeans contain
protein
so
for that you need enormous amounts of
soybean fields and how do you
plant the the
so much soybean drops by destroying
forests
so that is the reason why the amara
amazon rainforest is being destroyed
year after year i think every minute
several acres several acres of
rainforest are being destroyed in the
amazon
every single minute
and much of it is because of animal
agriculture agriculture
so i think it is terrible this obsession
with beef and meat
that the west has is destroying the
planet
uh
i think the per capita consumption of
meat in in let's say the us must be a
hundred times
the per capita consumption of meat in a
country like india maybe more than a
hundred times so if
the average indian average indian let's
say hypothetically consumes one one kilo
of meat per year
the average american would be consuming
more than 100 kilos of meat i don't have
the exact numbers but it's pretty close
to what i'm saying
right
and uh
and similarly with with the oceans we
are destroying the oceans we
are i mean uh i think we are extracting
hundreds of millions maybe billions of
tons of
uh
seafood you know fish and prawns and
krill and whatnot out of the oceans it's
destroying the oceans
it's destroying the balanced ecosystem
so uh
if it continues like this it's going to
destroy the planet and it's going to
cause a very very
a catastrophe
in the coming decades if it goes on like
this but you know who's gonna stop who's
gonna stop all this i'm not sure who
will
so that is the terrible situation that
we are in today
now when it comes to animals i i believe
it is my opinion that we should
consider any animals to be sentient
beings which they clearly are
they
have
they they
have a consciousness
they have an intellect of their own
they have thoughts they have feelings
they recognize people they have emotions
you simply cannot treat them the way
they are being treated
whether it's in the west whether it's
anywhere else
so yeah it's it's highly unethical and
it's it's incredibly extraordinarily
cool what's being done to them
okay
himank says what's the mystery behind
the lunar lake and what do you think
about the religious stories
associated with it okay what is lonar
lake let's go back to the map
where is the map and let's just
type it in lo nar crater or lake
whatever
so this is the place it is in
central india
as you can see it's more or less central
india it's in the deccan plateau
it is in the state of maharashtra in
india
and let's zoom in
so as you can see it's a reasonably
circular kind of lake
if you look at the satellite image
this is what we see
so this actually is not it is of course
the lake but what caused the formation
of this
roughly circular lake let's take a look
at the diameter of this lake how
wide is the lake
so that's approximately
over a kilometer one point one four one
point one five maybe one point two
kilometers in diameter so that's a
significant uh
significantly large
lake
from the diameter perspective it's
roughly circular so what what is this
thing this is an ancient impact crater
what is an impact crater it is a hole in
the
earth's surface
caused by the impact of an
extraterrestrial object typically
a meteorite a an asteroid a crate a
comet or some such object that comes
from outer space right so this so that
is what caused this crater to to exist
and uh initially it was thought that it
is it is the this crater was the result
of walk of ancient volcanism because
this region
is part of the deccan traps
so what are the deccan traps it is a
region of ancient volcanism in central
india
and this volcanism happened
approximately between 70 and 60 0.60
between 70 and 60 million years before
today it coincides with the cretaceous
paleogene extinction of the non-avian
dinosaurs
so it's today believed
that the extinction of the non-avian
dinosaur dinosaurs happened because of a
combination of two events
the indian volcanism the deccan traps
volcanism these were massive volcanoes
so one of the factors is the volcanism
in india and the other factor is the
chichulo impact event in yucatan
mexico which happened over here there is
this
ancient impact crater that you find
that is
present
over here you cannot see it on the map
because it's buried underground
but it has been detected it it very much
exists and its epicenter is around the
the village of chichalub
in yucatan
so the extinction
event of the non-avian dinosaurs
happened because of most likely because
of a combination of two causes the czech
impact and the deccan traps volcanism so
when this lonar crater was discovered
initially it was believed that this
crater was a consequence of that ancient
volcanism the deccan traps volcanism but
later it was discovered that it actually
uh
shows the characteristics of an impact
event and
it is believed that this impact happened
maybe 50 or 60 000 years before today
another more recent study i believe says
it happened about half a million years
before today so it's still a matter of
debate what it is
when it happened but it is clearly
uh caused by the impact of an inch the
impact of an extraterrestrial object
so that is what the lunar lake is that
is the
lunar crater how it was formed and also
there's no real mystery about it
uh
it is very much an impact crater it's
not a volcanic crater the only question
is when did this impact happen
was it 50 to 60 000 years before today
or was it like half a million years
before today so that is something that
needs to be determined properly right
now it's kind of a matter of debate
and what do i think about the religious
stories associated with it i have
absolutely no idea of religious stories
associated associated with it i see it
from the perspective of well geology and
science
i'm not aware of one of the religious
stories there may be some but
so yeah that's not what i am aware of
right
okay
next question
sauraj says
in india
we have beaches
mountains desert snow
amazing forests great monuments amazing
history and much more
india is heaven for food lovers
vegetarians as well as non-vegetarians
and indians are the most hospitable
people in the world
so despite all of this why is tourism in
india not doing so well
most more people visit other countries
why can't we harness the tourism economy
it will act as soft power for india
and give many jobs very good question i
have said this in the past i believe
that india has the potential to become a
genuine tourism superpower india can be
can become
if india gets its act together india can
become the world's number one tourism
destination the oldest civilization so
many things like you said mountains and
deserts and snow and beaches and forests
and islands great monuments
sports tourism great historical
monuments and
great culture great food great cuisine
so much that india can offer to people
from other countries so why is india not
a popular very popular tourism
destination i am not sure what the exact
statistics are but
i'm sure india is not quite in the top
10 in the world maybe not even the top
tourism destinations in the world it is
places like france and paris and greece
and what not
even
i believe
korea and japan south korea japan etc
that are like more popular tourism
destinations than india so why is it so
well it's it's actually quite simple our
infrastructure is terrible
if you're a tourist what do you want you
want good hotels you want good
infrastructure you if you if you want to
go to a certain destination it should be
easy to reach the place
right
let's say let forget about foreign
tourists let's say you are an indian
tourist in indian pilgrim let's say
let's say you you live in
let's say you live in new delhi
or let's say you live in chennai all
right so you live in chennai and you
want to go to the great uh
city the the great ancient uh town of
sumnat
where you have the the great ancient uh
temple right the jyotirling
you wanna go there shiri somnath judi
ling temple one of the greatest and
oldest
religious sites in india so let's say
you're in chennai you want to go to this
very famous destination somnath how do
you reach there
is there an airport in sumnat there is
none
where is the nearest airport i believe
it's in uh due is it
it may be in the yeah there's an airport
here
and then you so you have to either uh go
to the u
which is like how far is dio from zuma
let's just calculate the distance
so it's about 70 kilometers so the u is
one of the options or you go to large
code and then you travel by their so raj
code to somnath is about
161 170 kilometers if it goes straight
but obviously the road will not be
straight so you have to get down a raj
court or or do you and then take i don't
know a bus or
or a taxi or whatever and go to sunnah
it's so difficult
despite this being one of the most
important religious places in the
country and there are so many other
important places in the country
religious places and places of
touristic interest
but those places it's not really easy to
reach there and even if you're able to
somehow reach there where will you stay
are there good hotels available there
are the places safe enough at night
there are so many questions that one can
raise
so our infrastructure is terrible it is
not tourist friendly even if you go to a
big city like chennai mumbai you face
all kinds of problems as a tourist
uh
i mean you got to stand in in endless
skews for various things and there are
all kinds of problems right
and
yeah so so there are so many problems so
what india needs to do is india needs to
get its act together in build proper
infrastructure
make the country
tourist friendly inviting to tourists
not problematic for tourists no it
shouldn't they should not go back with
like
horror stories or anything i'm not
saying that there are horror stories
happening for tourists in india but you
know it's not a very pleasant experience
much of the time
so if you go to and if you contrast that
with a country like japan it's so
great for tourists if you go to paris if
you go to france we go to italy it's
such a great experience for a tourist
the infrastructure is great the hotels
are great even cheap
hotels are are still quite good and it's
very easy to get around
and so and so forth so
that's what needs to happen india needs
to get its act together and if india
does that then india can become a
tourism superpower
and if india becomes a tourism
superpower it's india's economy
will boom
because tourists are people who spend a
lot of money in your local economy they
come to your city or town or whatever
and they're gonna spend money there so
it's going to bring in foreign
money into the country
it's going to benefit the local people
the local shop owners the local business
owners
the problem
is that when it's local shop owners and
business owners who benefit
the politicians kind of feel left out
because the politicians
in many places in at least some places
in india
in some places at least in india the
politicians want a cut of everything
they want a percentage
i'm not saying it's that way everywhere
i'm sure there are lots of places in
india which are very clean and and no
corruption etc but there must be some
places right one years
from time to time
so then if the politicians are kind of
getting left out then they don't really
care about tourism then right because it
doesn't benefit them
so that's one of the reasons why tourism
doesn't do well historically it has not
done well in india
but i think there is tremendous
potential in india tremendous potential
for tourism
so one hopes that
india unlocks the tourism potential it
has and that would be great for the
economy for the country
for india's soft power like people say
we love soft power right we are obsessed
with soft power soft power is the most
important thing anyway so that's a
different story but yeah so india has
the potential one hopes that india will
unlock that potential and
let's see how that goes
okay
peace out says i am currently doing my
master's thesis in architecture at tu
delft i think it's in in the netherlands
i'm working on energy transition
infrastructure in the global south with
the focus on the case of india in your
opinion is transitioning from fossil
fuels to a more sustainable source of
energy
or even nuclear possible in the near
future if so what would it
what would it take in the case of india
see when you have
a country with a massive population like
china or india or any country with with
a significant population
if you if you you do have to provide for
their energy needs and in the case of
india and china historically we have
used coal we burned coal to generate
electricity and of course that has a
significant carbon footprint which is
not great in the long run
so we are burning fossil fuels mostly
right but we do need to transition from
fossil fuels to something more
sustainable something more green
so india has
embarked upon this this uh new path
the
india is the founding member the the
the of the solar alliance the solar
alliance is the brain chain the
brainchild of the of prime minister modi
i believe
and other countries are involved in that
and india has so much
sunlight
that it's it's conceivable that india
could be able to to generate as much
electricity as it needs from solar only
it's quite possible of course one would
need to develop better
solar cells and all that but uh yeah it
certainly is possible so solar energy is
is a big component of sustainable
sources of energy and the other
option obviously is nuclear now people
are scared of nuclear nuclear is bad why
is it bad you do it properly it's going
to work just fine
and of course india is a going forward
with building uh
more
newer reactors nuclear reactors i
believe
so as long as you take care of the
safety aspect and all of those things
properly then i think nuclear power is a
very good option for
green sustainable energy
so uh
so in my opinion is transitioning from
fossil fuels to
more sustainable sources possible in the
near future i think over the next decade
next two decades at most india should be
able to transition
to
uh
sustainable sources of energy
to a significant extent i would say that
more than 50 percent of india's energy
needs
in the next 10 20 years possibly could
be met by
sustainable sources of energy
so that's what i think
most likely will happen i think it
should happen all over the world there
are various ways of doing this
the easiest way is solar energy then you
also have wind energy hydro
uh
hydrothermal energy
hydropower
and
waves and piezoelectric all kinds of
exotic technologies as well
but one should keep things simple
focus on two or three things at most and
do that so i think
solar is a great bet for that and also
nuclear so i think that should be the
way forward for india
okay
chandrasekhar says last time you talked
about the proof of rebirth
and said that science doesn't accept it
because it can't be shown to everyone
but isn't the same thing true for
science as well
many of the complex mathematical proofs
aren't even accessible to one percent of
the world's population and they are so
tough that you have to spend years and
years to understand them by making
things extremely complex so that only a
few people in their respective branches
can understand isn't science also taking
power and control of authority albeit in
a cunning manner
okay this wonderful controversy we
revisited today let's see
so rebirth and uh so people
are very unhappy with science because
science says there is no evidence of
rebirth rebirth
okay so let's take a different approach
let's say
let's take a hypothetical case tk
a hypothetical case hypothetical
scenario
let's say there is this person
person x
who is
murdered
by somebody
and the case is never solved who
committed the murder it's never found
found out
but a few years later a child
starts claiming
that i was this person x
and i remember
my life i know all kinds of details
about the life of person x so i am
clearly the reincarnation of person x
and i know who committed the crime i
know who murdered me in my previous life
and the child needs a certain person why
so now can you go to court
can you go to a court of law
in india or any country in the world and
say that see i have this undeniable
testimony by this child who remembers
everything about his or her previous
life and his child has
proven
that so and so person why committed the
murder 10 years ago
will this evidence hold in a court of
law
in a court of law in india
or in any other country in the world it
will not hold they will laugh you off
and they'll throw out the case
why is that because there is no evidence
this is all hearsay
and i can i can assure you that even two
and a half thousand years before today
when you had an indian judicial system
in the mauryan empire in the in the
gupta empire in the in the empire even
in
india's indigenous legal system
such cases would have been thrown out
why is it so because there is no way of
of conclusively proving that this claim
by this child is true
what is the correct way of proving
reincarnation tell me
the only
correct way of proving reincarnation is
by
measuring this object called the soul
observing it and proving
that it has come out of person x who
died
and it it has entered person
zed who is a newborn
if you can conclusively demonstrate the
transmigration of the soul by observing
it
and measuring it that is the only way
you can actually prove that
reincarnation happens
that's how science works science has
certain criteria you don't don't like
those criteria don't believe it
but if you break the discipline of
science you will have no progress do you
understand something science is not
something something that has been
imposed upon india by the west science
emerged out of india thousands of years
ago
all our great maharishis like kannada
etc we're not crazy
they also have would have believed in
reincarnation or whatever but when you
when it comes to science it's only about
the material world you can have no
material progress
and your
cultures relation civilization can never
have any progress if you don't
develop science science is only about
the material observable empirical world
it's about material objects observable
objects and empirical evidence only
that's how science works you don't like
it disregard it
but you cannot say that science has to
be this way or that way
right
science has a certain discipline
and scientists are duty-bound to follow
the discipline the moment you stray from
the path you are no longer a scientist
you're a pseudoscientist
that is
just how it works
and the problem in india is that people
don't understand science there is this
incredible lack of scientific awareness
and scientific temperament on the one
hand
we are proud that we produce so many
scientists over the past few thousands
of years on the other hand we want to
question science
on one hand
we want india to progress materially
india's gdp should grow india should
develop more technology etc on the other
hand we want to say science should not
do this and science should not do that
science will do what science has to do
it has to do
you can you cannot say that science has
to be this way or that way
we are proud that we have been able to
develop so much technology nuclear
weapons
missiles of all kinds
aircraft fighter aircraft so and so
forth
if you do you think that it would have
been possible if we started bending the
rules of science and and doing things
without evidence
it doesn't work like that
now when it comes to mathematics uh many
of the complex mathematical proofs
aren't accessible to even one percent of
the world's population
so
are we making things complex
what exactly is mathematics
mathematics is
mathematics describes
the patterns and the regularities of the
observable universe that's what it does
you don't make mathematics complex
you investigate and discover mathematics
and it reveals to you the nature of the
universe
so it's not like we are creating complex
mathematics
mathematics is something that we
discover
and whatever we discover we have to
accept it
and it is complex
it's not complex because we want it to
be complex i mean you can do mathematics
at any level you want you can stay at
the two plus two equal to four level
or you can learn multiplication division
on all that or you could learn
trigonometry or you could progress to
algebra but as you go deeper and deeper
into math you actually start discovering
the true complexity of the universe
right
and it is complex it's not complex
because we want it to be complex the
question people ask it's it's very
popular nowadays is mathematics invented
or discovered
mathematics
is discovered
mathematics is simply what the universe
is it tells us what the universe is
of course we invent certain tech
techniques
of solving certain mathematical problems
so that's what we invent we invent
techniques but the actual math that we
that is revealed to us is discovered
we are discovering the true nature of
the universe it is complex it is complex
you can choose to not see it if you find
it most people would find it extremely
complex because math is difficult it's
extremely difficult it's very complex
but it's not like scientists are trying
to
uh what is that trying to take control
of authority and all that no it's just
the way it is
you go to higher levels in any
discipline
you cannot be the one person of the one
person and only one person of the one
person will be able to understand things
at the highest elite level in any
discipline in any field whether it is
physics whether it's chemistry whether
it's mathematics whether it is
accounting whether it is
entrepreneurship or whatever whether
it's build a business whether it's
athletics
the elite performers will will be a very
few
so that's just how it is
so i think we need to take a few steps
back and stop bashing science without
science there is no progress india is
the birthplace of science and
mathematics and astronomy and all of
that
calculus trigonometry
the things that you find very complex
they came out of india they were
discovered by indian scientists
so
see it's up to you at the end of the day
you want to believe it you want to
believe in reincarnation believe
if you don't believe in science don't
believe in science but
let's let's stay out of what other
people are doing
would you like scientists to come and
tell you how you should
what sort of belief systems you should
have
and the truth is
i mean there is this very very popular
and common view that people hold
that all scientists are atheists
and scientists don't believe in god and
scientists are this and that
what are you talking about
you can believe in god and yet be a
scientist
why can't you
there are so many scientists very very
great scientists who have
been believers in god
uh
ecg sudarshan
george sudarshan who was denied the
nobel prize three times
he was an advaita vedantin
he was a firm believer in vedanta
srinivas ramanujan one of the greatest
geniuses in mathematics
was a firm believer in hinduism
then i can give you lots of other
examples so if if you believe
in dharma in religion
if you believe in reincarnation it
doesn't mean you cannot be a scientist
these are separate matters
when you do science you do it with a
certain discipline and there are certain
rules that you to follow
so
as lay people you one has to stay out of
things we don't understand and as
scientists
we have to stay out of
questions of culture
and and belief in faith
so these are separate worlds
both have to respect each other's
perspective
because scientists in science are very
important
without science you will have no
progress whatsoever so i would urge
people whether you believe or not in
reincarnation in god or whatever you
should try and understand what the
scientific method is
you should try and understand what
science is it helps it helps a lot in a
variety of ways in life
so that's what i would have to say about
this
okay they just says what are brown
dwarfs are they planets or are they
stars a good question so brown dwarfs
are essentially fade stars
they are
stellar subs you could say substellar
objects
um
their mass is between 13 to 80 times
13 to 85 or 80
times the mass of jupiter so jupiter is
the largest planet in our solar system
it's a gas giant
and it is too small
to ignite nuclear
fusion
within its core
right because to ignite nuclear fusion
of hydrogen into helium you need
enormous amounts of pressure to fuse the
atoms together
so jupiter it's its mass is too too
small
to ignite fusion
but once you cross 13 times the mass of
jupiter
you are able to ignite a certain kind of
fusion you can
create you can
when an object is 13 times or more the
mass of jupiter
then you can have the fusion of
deuterium
into helium-3 within the core of that
object
if it's a gaseous object so brown dwarfs
are
large
gaseous objects
that are between 13 to 85 or so times
the mass of jupiter
and they cannot cause they're not quite
massive enough to sustain them to ignite
the nuclear fission fusion of hydrogen
into helium but they are able to fuse
deuterium into
helium-3 and
they uh so
so they're not very luminous much of
their their their energy output is in
the infrared wavelengths
and
they cool down over time so their their
the nuclear fusion phase
lasts for about 10 20 million years or
so after which they no longer undergo
fusion and they slowly slowly slowly
cool down
so that is what a brown dwarf it is it
is essentially a failed star it is
somewhere between a jupiter-like planet
and an actual star
somewhere in between it has some form of
fusion the fusion of deuterium
into helium-3 but not the fusion of
hydrogen into helium which is what
powers
uh
all regular stars so that's what a brown
dwarf is in very brief so they are not
planets they are failed stars
okay anime says uh
for an astronomy enthusiast can you
recommend a good telescope to observe
planets and the moon
how should one look for it how much
would a reasonably good telescope cost
what are the things when we should look
for while buying a telescope you know
what
i have always wanted to have a telescope
i've wanted to have one since i was like
two years old but i have never actually
had
a telescope never once
i've never owned a telescope so it's one
of the great
tragedies of my life i never had a
telescope
so uh personally i have no experience
with telescopes but i do understand how
telescopes work
so the most important thing you want to
look for in a telescope is the aperture
of the telescope which is the size of
the
lens
or the mirror of your telescope the size
means the diameter so let me give you an
example we have two space telescopes in
operation right now the hubble space
telescope and the
james webb
telescope
so the james webb telescope is way more
powerful than hubble because its
mirror
has a much larger diameter so when your
mirror or your lens is larger you can
collect more light
and you can see further so distant
objects will appear brighter so the most
important characteristics or feature or
specification of a telescope is the size
of the is is the size of the lens or the
mirror which is called the aperture of
the telescope so that is the most
important thing you want to look for in
a telescope obviously if you have a
telescope with a very large aperture
then it
becomes a very large telescope you
cannot transport it you can't carry it
around you have to install it in a
building i'm sure you want a telescope
that's not enormous something reasonably
sized so so then your the aperture of
your telescope will not be really
enormous it will be
moderate small to moderate size that's
what
astronomy enthusiasts would typically
use
and then you have something called the f
ratio which is the uh
ratio
which is the which is the telescope's
focal length divided by the aperture
right so the smaller your f ratio is the
smaller your magnification the higher
your f ratio is the higher your
magnification and the further away you
can see
and the narrower is your field of focus
so these are the characteristics that
typically define a telescope that's what
you learn in optics in physics
so
so i i'm not really sure how much a
reasonably good telescope would cost but
that's what i can
offer you from
the
theoretical knowledge that i have i
don't have any actual practical
knowledge i've never had a telescope
but it's it's great that you're
interested in astronomy so i would say
you should
buy a telescope
i mean whatever your budget is the best
telescope you can buy with a reasonably
good aperture
and a good f ratio
so that's what i could offer you
shweta says what's your perspective
about existence in human life if is it
mere buildup of moments which become
hours days months and years
or is human life a timeline of memory do
we live in memories how would we be if
there were no memories my mom mentions
that your last session in geopolitics
was extremely good thank you to your mom
frieda
so um
the perspective of existence in human
life
is human life merely
a timeline of memory do we live in
memories
what would we be if there were no
if there were no memories we would not
be ourselves
uh our understanding of the world
depends on our past experiences by
experiencing a variety of events
and
experiences we accumulate memories
which tell us the which which which
offer us recurring patterns of the of
the of
of existence
so how does the world work how do people
behave
by experiencing these things multiple
times we build up a storehouse or or a
dictionary
or a database of various patterns and
the more
we build this database the better we
become at handling the world
so without memory that simply won't work
if you have no memory you will have no
understanding of language you will now
have no concept of who you are
so memory is integral to your sense of
self to your functioning as a
functioning human being and to your
consciousness
so if you can only
perceive things but you can't store the
information then i think you're not
quite human right
so i think memory is integral to human
existence
and of course it all builds up from
moments which becomes which become hours
and days and months and years and the
older you get the faster time seems to
go that's one of the quirks of human
existence when you're a little child a
day can
once a single day can seem to last
forever but if you are 70 years old even
a year seems to go by in a flash
so that is one of the interesting quirks
of human existence
so memory is integral to our to our
consciousness and to our
uh our
status as as thinking living
perceiving existing
human beings so memory is very important
your timeline of memory is not
quite linear
it it's not always linear and you don't
always retrieve your memories in a
linear fashion some memories are more
strong or stronger some are kind of
weaker you don't think of certain things
often than the memories become hazy and
weak
so
so that's how it is and that is the
mystery of consciousness what exactly is
consciousness memory is obviously an
integral part of consciousness
that is what shapes our world view of
our understanding of the world
so memory is
integral and central to all of this for
sure
raghav says when a person learns
something and gains knowledge does that
person become more polite or more
egoistic
well it depends on the person on your
personality on your character
some people would become more egoistic
some people would become
more humble more polite it depends on
the person everybody is different
everybody reacts differently to various
things some people
once they read a couple of books they
say like um i'm an expert now i'm an
expert
i know everything some people are like
that
other people
they feel that the more they learn the
less they know because the more they
become aware of how much more there is
to learn
right so it depends on the person some
people become very egoistic
especially when they get a degree of
some kind
because some people
are all about status and certificates
and degrees give you status oh now i am
recognized as a scholar and so and so
so um
so obviously the question is not about
degrees and certificates it's about
knowledge
so uh you know what they say uh
half knowledge is is very dangerous or
whatever and unfortunately everybody
only has half knowledge nobody has all
the knowledge in their field or anything
like that
i personally find that the more i read
and the more i learn the more i realize
how much there is to learn and how much
i don't know
right i have this entire back catalog
backlog of books that i want to read
if i actually succeed in reading all of
them it's gonna take like 10 plus years
at my speed my speed is quite
rapid
and obviously i don't have all day to
read so it's like that so
i personally feel from my own personal
perspective that the more i learn things
the more i become aware of how much i
don't know and how much there is to
learn
and how little the the breadth and width
of my knowledge is
uh i don't think i'm a very egoistic
person arrogant person i at least that's
what i feel i it's up to you to judge
all that
so i think it's it's up to the
individual person everybody reacts
differently everybody
uh
yeah so that's how it is some people
will become
arrogant egoistic i know so much
i've done all this
and some people would become more humble
so that's how it is it's all about human
nature there are a variety of
there's a whole range a whole spectrum
of human nature
so it depends on where the person is
on the spectrum
okay kashyapa gotram reek says please
please please please answer this who
were the vanaras
were they neanderthals or monkeys well
how do we know
so
if you want to answer a question about
an event that happened thousands of
years ago
and
the question is about a certain
population of of people then you would
need some
tangible physical evidence of those
people
maybe
a burial maybe a skeleton or so
in which case you have a physical object
that you can
measure observe analyze and then you
could answer
right
so in the case of the
vanaras from the ramayana time we don't
as of today have any physical evidence
of these people right
so the question is were the neanderthals
or monkeys well obviously we don't know
that
in the 21st century even the 20th
century even in the past 2000 years
there is no evidence of any talking
monkeys
talking monkeys speaking monkeys or even
near north halls so that's the history
of the past 2000 years now what does the
word vanner mean
in
india's civilization language sanskrit
it's it's a sanskrit word we use it in a
variety of indian languages even today
but the word comes from sanskrit and the
meaning of the word warner is somebody
who dwells in a forest
somebody who who lives in a one one
means forest or jungle
so the real meaning of the word vaner is
a forest dweller it doesn't mean monkey
today it has become it has come to mean
monkey but it doesn't really mean monkey
the actual meaning is a forest dweller
so most likely the vanaras who helped
lord ram in his quest to
defeat the evil demon king robin these
warners were most likely forest dwellers
i do not believe that they were monkeys
they were most likely a population of
forest dwelling people
who
helped lord ram in his great quest
so that's
what i can say from the uh
meaning of the word in sanskrit and we
have absolutely no evidence of whether
they were monkeys or neanderthals we
have no
evidence that points in this direction
or that so it's mere speculation but as
we know
there is no evidence of any talking
monkeys or
monkeys with human-like intelligence
anywhere in the world
so
the simplest
and most logical
solution or answer is that these were
a population of forest dwelling human
beings
okay satyam bharadwaj says why is it
why is it so that certain species of
giant beaver hearts eagle
megalanya prisca
neanderthals etc have gone extinct
despite being much stronger than their
counterparts such as the
north american beaver stellars sea eagle
komodo dragon homo sapiens which
continue to exist
is it in consonance with darwin's
survival of the fittest theory
hmm so you are giving examples of
various species of animals etc
that were large and strong
and yet they went extinct
and their smaller weaker counterparts
still
exist today and still survive today why
is it so
doesn't it
prove that darwin's theory
of the survival of the fittest is
incorrect does it mean that
good question
see
it's like this
large
doesn't always mean
fit
size doesn't indicate fitness it doesn't
necessarily indicate fitness
think of this image in your mind
a sumo wrestler
or sumo wrestler is a very large
individual but is that person really fit
i wonder what is the average
life expectancy of a sumo wrestler
is it the same as your normal human
being is it higher or is it lower i
would guess
that the average life expectancy of a
sumo wrestler must be lower than the
average
regular lay person
so size doesn't necessarily indicate
fitness
sometimes leaner is meaner and fitter
right
so uh
and it's not only about the size it's
also about the intelligence the
adaptability
for instance if you give the example of
neanderthals for whatever reason homo
sapiens turned out to be
longer lasting than neanderthals or
cousins of course
many
non-african humans have some neanderthal
genes which is a whole different story
so the the simple answer is that size
doesn't necessarily indicate fitness
there have been so many large large
large animals that have gone extinct for
instance when there is an extinction
event like the event like the uh
paleogene cretaceous extinction event 66
million is before before today all of
the large dinosaurs died out they could
not survive that event
but the smaller
dinosaurs that the avian dinosaurs
survived it
they survived the terrible catastrophe
and they still exist today
dinosaurs still exist as of today
similarly a bunch of small rat like
mammals
also survived that extinction event and
their descendants are using
all this technology today it's us
so
size doesn't always indicate fitness
fitness
is a whole bunch of a variety of various
factors
and it depends on what what the
environment is like right now
so that's why sometimes it's the smaller
species the apparently weaker species
that turn out to be fitter and they
survive longer
okay
varun says when are you launching your
course in physics your way of explaining
is just awesome
do consider this i i as a student of
physics in waiting for that thank you so
much uh i don't have any immediate plans
of launching any course in physics right
i think the majority of the people would
want me to launch a course in history or
on
book in history or a variety or a number
of courses and books in history i think
i would have to do that first because
most people are not interested in
science most people are interested in
indian history
so i think i should do that first
eventually i don't mind launching a
course in
in physics or astrophysics or something
something that can be understood by
everybody so that's something i will do
most likely eventually but right now i
should
definitely focus on
history for now
but thank you very much for the
suggestion and thank you
krishna says tell us about norse
mythology and vikings like eric the red
and the lothbrocks so
norse mythology is the mythology of the
viking of those of the
scandinavian people the vikings
and the simplest way of
understanding norse mythology
is to imagine ancient indian mythology
but transport that
to a land of ice and snow
that's it
that's norse mythology the same gods
with different names
and they live in a land of ice and snow
and midnight sun
i'm going all led zeppelin right here
so
in norse mythology
there is this indian god who becomes a
viking god the indian god
has two weapons
one is the thunderbolt
called vajra in sanskrit
and the other is the hammer
also called the vajra in sanskrit this
god obviously is indra
he becomes thor
in norse mythology and a variety of
other gods the entire
vedic pantheon of gods essentially is
present in norse mythology
so just imagine indian ancient indian
vedic mythology and transport all of
those gods
into a land where there is ice and snow
in midnight sun that is norse mythology
that's how can how i can describe it in
brief now
you're asking what eric the red in the
lothbrocks
a sailor
and he happened to be the first person
across the so-called atlantic ocean
and he happened to be the first
european in recorded history
to see
north america with his own eyes
so he went all the way west
and he was able to see north america but
he did not actually land there he went
back because of scarcity of rations
because he was running out of provisions
and all that most likely
so eric the red is the first european
first white men in in recordedly
and his son
leif eriksson
then followed in his father's footsteps
and he actually landed in north america
in most likely in newfoundland in
present day canada
and they have found an ancient viking
archaeological site in north america
it's called
lost their meadows or something like
that
so that is the story of eric the red and
his son leif eriksson
now when it comes to the loth brocks
you're talking about ragnar lothbrok
so ragnar block was a legendary viking
warrior raider and king
he launched a number of raids into
england
and he became the king of the vikings of
the scandinavians and he was a very
legendary fighter a legendary figure he
is considered by the by mysteries by
historians to be a semi-mythical or
semi-legendary king of the vikings
that's how historians portray him
and his son bjorn ironside
well he was one of the great kings of
sweden of the vikings
his uh
bjorton's
tomb or or barrow still stands somewhere
in sweden i believe
and
ragnar lothbrok he met a very strange
death he was captured by
an english king
was it from northumbria
king ella i think
who captured him eventually and he
he put him in a pit full of vipers or
snakes and he was bit bitten by the
snakes to death
so that's how the story goes so that is
the story of ragnar lothbrok then he was
killed by this english king so his sons
so ragnar's sons then decided to take
revenge for their father's death and
they invaded the british islands
there was called the great
viking invasion of the great hidden
invasion or something like that
something like that and they were able
to invade and conquer england and
plunder the land
so that is in brave the story of
ragnar lothbrok and his sons
and his sons
one of them was obviously like i said
bjorn ironside
and then there was this guy called ivar
the boneless
and a few other sons as well
sigur the snake in the eye
so these are the names of his sons and i
think there's this wonderful serial
called vikings right
that has popularized these ancient
stories
so yeah
that in brief is the answer
all right
is it true ashish says is it true that
someone who understands science will
understand other subjects
the vice versa is not true so is it true
that a person who understands science
will understand all other subjects
but a person who doesn't understand
science will not understand other
subjects not quite true
you can be a great scientist and you
will not you may not understand anything
about art
you may be a great physicist
but you will be a terrible football
manager
you may be a great mathematician but you
may end up being a terrible businessman
or businesswoman
so it's not necessary that if you
understand science well that you will
understand all other subjects very well
not quite so not quite
so of course an understanding of the
scientific method is
very valuable and beneficial in a
variety of ways in life but it's not
always the case that if you are great at
science that you will be great at
everything else
right okay karthik says you talk about
discoveries and inventions made by our
ancestors also please talk about
astrology i get this question a lot
unfortunately i know nothing about
astrology
it's something i've never studied i've
honestly never been interested in
so uh
i'm sure it's very interesting and
there must be a lot to learn in it but i
don't know anything about it so i just
took this question to put this on the
record
i don't know anything about astrology
someone says thoughts on premium
possessions do you collect any of it
cars or watches
my premium collections possessions are
books
i connect books this is just a small
sample of the books that i have i have
other bookshelves in other places in my
house
so i have a whole lot of books that's
the premium possessions i collect
i don't collect cars or watches i have a
watch that i bought
18 years or so ago i still use it it's
not a cheap watch but
i i buy things that last so i am not
quite a collector of anything else i
don't collect anything else the only
thing i collect is books so it's up to
you
if you like collecting things then
collect things some people like to
collect wine bottles some people collect
watches some ladies collect shoes they
have thousands of pairs of shoes some
people want to buy expensive cars so it
depends on your personal tastes and
[Music]
all that
so for me it's books
books
shankarajit gaushtasthidar says how do
you remain motivated on your goals
and read so much i keep losing
motivation in a few days and i lost the
habit of reading books which i had
before
after so much of electronic device usage
at work at home
nowadays i can only read a couple of
pages at a time please help
see it's about stamina even
when it comes to reading books it takes
a certain amount of mental stamina if
you lose the habit
if you lose the discipline of reading
every day then your
mental stamina will decrease
and then you will not be able to
read more than two three pages a day
so if you build a habit you have to keep
on sustaining the habit and in that case
you're able to you'll be able to read
more you may even actually be able to
read faster now how do you remain
motivated
and you're saying that you lose
motivation in a few days well
you can't motivate me to do things i
don't like
right
i mean there are plenty of activities
that i don't enjoy at all and
i will never ever be motivated to do
that
but some things so so what is it that
motivates people
two things
either you enjoy the process of whatever
you're doing or you are going towards an
end result that is really attractive
so for let's take a hypothetical example
bodybuilding
bodybuilding is a painful process you go
to gym you lift weights every day heavy
weights it's painful your muscles ache
you have aches and pains every day and
that's a lot of hard work it's physical
labor that you're doing in the gym like
two hours a day or whatever it takes and
you do it for months and months and
months on end
actually you do it for years on end so
why do people do that
why do they not lose motivation
some people enjoy the process of
bodybuilding going to gym lifting
weights it's fun for some people some
people enjoy the muscular pain that they
experience they enjoy the muscular pump
that they get in the gym
so they enjoy the process or
they may look forward to the end result
i want to be a massive superhuman being
so i'm willing to put myself through the
pain because i have this very attractive
goal
that is waiting for me at the end of the
road
so that's an example from bodybuilding
so either you enjoy the process or you
have a very
attractive end result that you
desperately seek or it's a combination
of both factors
so you cannot remain motivated in
something that
you don't enjoy or whose end result
doesn't
appeal to you
right
so maybe it is that there is no real
tangible benefit for you
from reading books
maybe maybe it could be that way i'm
just i'm just guessing i don't really
know what
what your what your uh
i i don't really know you so i'm
guessing that maybe
maybe perhaps hypothetically
you may not quite know what you want to
get out of reading books
so for me it was just curiosity i mean i
just enjoy the process of reading books
that's what that's what it's been like
for me i really enjoy the process of
discovery
i really enjoy
reading books it's like going on a
journey for me so that's why i've always
been able to sustain that habit
but if you ask me to do something else
like peel potatoes
well you won't see any motivation from
me
so it's all that's how it is
so don't force yourself to do things you
don't really enjoy when it comes to
electronic devices and all that yeah
that's that's a problem these days there
are so many distractions there is so
much cheap
instant gratification
instant entertainment scroll up scroll
up scroll up watch this 30 second video
scroll up so watch the second watch the
next 30 second video and you can do that
endlessly on loop for hours and hours
you need to break free of that that is
simply
uh
it's an addiction
addiction to the dopamine release that
you get from watching these uh videos
that actually
don't help you grow in any way and don't
offer you any real value
so
that is something you have to figure out
for yourself how to break free of that
and if obviously if you spend so much
time doing that you will not have time
to do anything else which is which may
be more valuable to you
so you need to find a way of breaking
free of
these habits maybe you can delete those
apps from your phone that's a good idea
so yeah
says what's the best
diet to follow for a 20 year old to gain
weight it's very simple if you want to
gain weight eat more and lift weights
that's the solution eat more lift
weights obviously it's not as simple as
that you do eat right
so let's say you're 20 years old and
whatever you're eating it keeps you at a
certain weight so try and eat 20 more
food and eat the right food eat more
protein
eat less
processed carbohydrates
eat cut out all the refined
carbohydrates eat lots of vegetables eat
more protein i'm not sure if you're
vegetarian or non-vegetarian if you are
a non-vegetarian meat-eater you have
only a few options for protein sources
if you are a vegetarian you have way
more options
for protein
so depending on what you are you can
tailor your diet to your needs but
obviously if you want to gain weight you
have to eat more than what you're eating
very simple
very simple try and eat twenty percent
more than what you're eating for the
next three months and see how it goes
and obviously
if you want this weight gain to be
sustainable you have to go to gym and
lift weights like you to go in a you
start a weight training program
and it has to be a weight training
program that's tailored to your body
structure and all that everybody has a
different metabolism different genetics
and so on so forth so everybody is
different
so that's what i can say in brief
obviously you should follow proper
medical advice have a good trainer
hopefully
and yeah so that
is the general principle of how you
would how you would
succeed in gaining weight and obviously
it will not happen in two weeks three
weeks
give yourself one year
these changes are slow
so so it's possible it is certainly
possible depending on your genetics
metabolism
it's certainly possible for you to gain
10 kilos of muscle mass in a year if you
eat the right kind of food and follow
the right
weight training program very much
possible at
the age of 20.
so all the best all the best
okay the indian critic says wisdom
versus power which is greater
usually people imagine an ideal world
and say that wisdom is greater than
power but in reality there are many
examples where power defeated wisdom
so basically give opinions not on your
bases but on the basis of reality on
this controversial topic and please say
the truth because truth is bitter
okay sir i will try to say the truth
why is this topic controversial
i see nothing controversial about this
so what is greater wisdom or power
wisdom or power
if you have wisdom see
what really matters in life
it doesn't matter how wise you are
what truly matters in your life
is what impact you have on the real
world
you are born not to observe you are born
to participate
in the world
and if you just sit at home and observe
and become very wise by reading books
but you don't use that wisdom for
anything then your life is pointless
your existence is essentially pointless
because it will it will be as good as
not having existed
if you have if you leave behind no
legacy or have no impact on the world or
on the society in any way whatsoever
so the true
measure
of your
of your of of
the impact you have in your in your life
is how you
affect society
whether you impact society in any way or
not whether you change the world in any
way or not that is a true measure of how
valuable your life was
so if you only have wisdom
but you have no power to do anything
then you will be able to do nothing in
your life
so power is
definitely very important if you have
power then you can effect changes in
your life in in your life in the lives
of others in society in the world
so wisdom without power is useless it's
pointless
but power without wisdom is also very
dangerous but even if you have no wisdom
and you have power you can still change
society for good or for bad
so greater what is greater power is
always greater
power is always greater
of course one would want a person who is
powerful to also be wise
that would be the ideal situation
but a person who is wise and has no
power
is meaningless
a person who is powerful but is not wise
can still change the world in some ways
in many ways
so which is greater wisdom or power
power is greater
okay they just says how can one find
strength within and stop being
demotivated are you always in a happy
state of mind
do you ever feel like not coming on live
streams and cancelling them because
you're not feeling like doing them
do you ever feel you are not good enough
hmm good questions
am i always in a happy state of mind i
am usually in a happy state of mind i'm
a very positive person but obviously
life is not all
nice things
life is full of ups and downs i have
been through my ups and downs life's not
always been pretty
but i am a very positive person overall
so yeah right now i am in a happy state
of mind i'm happy
and do i ever feel like not coming on
streams and cancelling them because i
don't feel like doing them
sometimes in the middle of the week or
so i may feel kind of lazy and shall i
do it this week or not but
when the weekend comes i do my live
streams on weekends as you guys know
by the time the weekend comes i'm always
motivated because i enjoy this i enjoy
this process of interacting with you all
of answering your questions taking your
questions and dealing with various
interesting topics so i really enjoy
this process and since i enjoy this
process i am not like
i don't feel demotivated
so it's never been
ever that i i did not feel like coming
on a live stream or canceling a live
stream it's never happened once or twice
i have been like ill i caught a virus a
couple of times once or twice i was
traveling that's why i had to cancel
streams but apart from that i have not
cancelled any streams since i started
apart from these two three instances
and
once i did a live stream when i had 104
degree fever
i never spoke about this because there's
no point it's it's it doesn't concern
you
the first podcast that i did on this
channel with anuj
it's a
the first one
so when i did that i had 104 degree
fever but i still came because well
i i gave you my word so i should keep it
so it's about being professional it's
about enjoying the thing so uh
i have never felt like cancelling a
stream
i've canceled streams only when it was
inevitable when i had no option
or do i ever feel that i am not good
enough i don't quite feel that i'm not
good enough i always feel that i have to
improve i always feel that there is
something that i can do better there's a
lot i can do better i always have this
feeling that i am getting in this
comfort zone and i'm taking things
lightly or i'm taking things for granted
i should do something different
i should take on more responsibilities
do something else
so
that is a feeling that i always have but
i don't ever feel that i'm not good
enough
i think i'm reasonably good enough
i'm not great i'm not some super genius
i'm not some
or whatever you know like super expert
super genius but
i am reasonably good
reasonable
so that's how i feel i
i
am i don't consider myself an expert in
anything i consider myself a student i
am learning things and i'm sharing
whatever i'm learning
so if you have that attitude then you
will not feel that you have to be the
best
right
so
so that's where i am how do i find
strength and not stop being demotivated
uh
i am
not demotivated
what what is what exactly does
demotivated mean when it means that you
have some goal
but you kind of don't feel like
pursuing it anymore so you lose the
motivation
to reach the goal so that is
demotivation
so that will happen when your goal is
not interesting enough
or
or it doesn't fit with your values
right
when you have a certain worldview you
have certain values inside you and you
are pursuing a certain goal but you are
pursuing it for the wrong reasons then
you will not have the motivation
maybe it's your family who wants you to
do this thing or maybe it's society that
expects certain things from you and
that's why you're trying to do it you're
doing it to impress other people even
though you don't actually like it
in that case you will not be motivated
so i'm just giving examples i'm not
guessing what what it is that
if what you are going through i
obviously don't know that i'm just
giving hypothetical examples so in such
cases you would feel demotivated so the
trick is to find an objective a big
objective like a 10 year objective
that really really comes from within you
that you want from within from deep
inside and you want to do it for
yourself
not for somebody else
so if you can find that sort of thing
that sort of goal that sort of big
objective then you will not feel
demotivated
so that is what i can say i hope that
helps sir
okay let us take some
live chat questions
where was it i saw something interesting
yeah there it is
do you believe in ghosts
well i don't know
have i ever seen a ghost
not quite sure
so
do i have evidence that ghosts don't
exist
do i have
unequivocal evidence that ghosts don't
exist i don't
maybe they do who knows
i don't understand the entire universe
i don't even understand one person of
the universe what it is like what drives
it so i
what i would say is that i don't know
i am ghost agnostic
i have never quite
quite
experienced a ghost for 100 sure
but i can't say that they don't exist so
yeah i am ghost agnostic
all right
video is not clear really again
is the video clear it is not clear
that would be terrible if that would be
the case
okay
where do i get my t-shirts i
usually buy them from
shops sometimes online
why is the video quality not clear what
is this
is it not clear
let me try and change
okay can you see me
terrible since the beginning it's the
second time that's happened that's
terrible
anyhow let's take some more questions i
hope you guys can see me
um
how can we take kailash from china
how can we take kailash from china well
we would have to take tibet from china
we would have to free tibet
and uh so yeah that's something that
will that will hopefully happen in the
future
it's certainly not going to happen
anytime
soon
okay
the video quality is better now all
right that's great
who discovered water on the moon
chandrayaan one or sophia telescope i
have never heard of sophia telescope but
as far as i know it was the
chandrayaan-1
lunar orbiter that discovered
water on moon
okay let's take some other questions
if we believe in god we have to believe
in ghosts too right well i don't know
i have no idea
well if you have experienced the ghost
they will have to believe it
i guess
so i think it's about your personal
experiences if somebody has actually
met a ghost or seen a ghost or
experienced a ghost then whether they
believe in god or not they will have to
believe in a ghost
so it all depends on your personal
experience
so so that that's
most likely what it would be like
jake says is there anything wrong
morally in building a career abroad
there's nothing wrong with it
for most people you have to pursue
what's best for you in life whether it's
in india whether it's somewhere else of
course it's nice to be patriotic and
build your country but hey it's your
life it's your choice i don't see
anything morally wrong with it if you
want to move abroad and build a career
there
so it's entirely up to you sir
why did you just delete your discord
server please answer i deleted it
because i was not able to participate i
had not logged in for months i'm so busy
now i have created this i had created
this discord server community
in my name
in which i was never ever present
and a whole bunch of other people were
running it i don't i did not even know
what was happening there
that is very irresponsible actually in a
way
that i create a community in my name and
i never participate there
and then what i found is that yesterday
i got a message from discord saying that
one of the administrators
was trying to take ownership
of the server
so that's when i thought that it's so
it's it's been enough time i don't know
what's happening there and if somebody
hijacks the server
then god knows what they will do in my
name
so since i was unable to participate
in the discord community because of my
terrible
paucity of time
and because i had no idea what was
happening there i think i
it was the right decision to delete the
server
because well
either you take the responsibility or
you or you don't so i was not in a
position to take the responsibility
so that's why i did that sir
do you like do you like lord of the
rings yes i like it
the book the movie
the movies were very good the book is
also great of course there are certain
problematic aspects in the book
uh there you can see that there is this
latent white supremacism
of the writer that sometimes creeps
through in the writing
but overall it's a great it's a great
great book great story one of the great
uh achievements in literature
difference between raja samrad and
chakravarthy samrat a chakra
is an emperor who conquers territories
and lands in all directions
a raja or a samrat is a local king so
the difference between a king and an
emperor a king is a raja or a samrat
a chakravarthy samarat is an emperor who
conquers a great great territory a great
empire
so one could say that uh chandragupta
maurya was a chakravartism
ashok maurya whether do you like him or
not was a chakra because he had an
enormous empire
chula
right
so that is the difference between a
simple raja
and a chakravarti samarat
that's the difference between a maharaja
and a maharaja
right
are indian gulab jamuns better than the
pakistani ones i have never eaten
pakistani gulab jamuns so no idea but i
am sure our gulab jamuns are better than
the pakistani ones obviously
right let's take some other questions
whoa
okay
uh which other questions should i take
where's the indian stock market heading
i hope that it's going in the right
direction
towards the bull phase other than rather
than a bare face but i am not quite an
expert in these things so maybe you
should not ask me
why do whales and big mammals not get
cancer that's an interesting question
i hear that that
blue whales the largest mammal that we
know of
i hear that blue whales don't get cancer
and even elephants most likely don't get
it i am not quite sure why that's a very
interesting question
maybe i will look it up try and research
this because yeah it's something that
one should know about
so good question they just i don't quite
have the answer today but i will try and
look it up and hopefully answer in a
subsequent episode
is god exists give answering yes or no
the answer is a definite maybe
i don't know man i don't know
i don't know i've never seen or
experienced god it doesn't mean god
doesn't exist maybe i'm just too small
to experience something so great
right
i am just a small
tiny insignificant human being with a
very limited intellect
and very very rudimentary perception
maybe i'm just too small
and insignificant to understand or
comprehend or
experience
god so i
don't know i have never experienced
any material manifestation physical
manifestation of god
but hey that doesn't mean god doesn't
exist
there is no way that i can
answer for sure because i haven't
because i
i don't know
you can give a yes or no answer if you
can understand the entire universe and
maybe what's beyond the universe i can't
so i don't know
i hope god exists that would be great
but
sadly
personally i've never experienced god
myself
okay
what else do we have
can europe
ban russian oil well they can try to ban
russian oil but they are deeply
dependent on russian energy whether it's
oil whether it's gas
so if they do stop
buying russian oil and gas they will
have to acquire it for a much higher
price
from the us or from the saudis or
somewhere else and the saudis are not
willing to ramp up their oil production
even though the americans want them to
so that creates a big dilemma for the
americans in their wasal states and for
for western europe so as of today i most
likely europe is enough as as of two
days of right now europe is between a
rock and a hard place
they are completely completely dependent
on russia for energy
but the americans want them to stop
buying russian energy
so
right now
the energy prices are skyrocket not
skyrocketing but they are rising
significantly in europe energy is
becoming more expensive
there may be the need for rationing and
cutting down on energy expenditure in
europe and overall everything is going
to be more expensive there's going to be
inflation prices are going to rise
so that's where we are
maybe they can ban russian oil to great
pain to themselves because they will
have to buy american oil or other oil at
much higher prices than what the
russians would
sell them oil at
so yeah that's the situation in europe
can you please explain the battles of
khan joel hill and the battle of red
hill i don't know about conjol hill but
if you are talking about the battle of
red hill
i think you are talking about a battle
that happened
in the mid-1940s
on the outskirts of the city of imphal
in manipur i think that's what you're
mentioning
so this was a battle that happened
between
the british indian army
in the invading japanese army
it happened
at a hill called red hill
i've been there personally
and it was a terrible battle and the
japanese lost at the end there is a
japanese memorial there where japanese
people still come from time to time to
to pay their tributes to their fallen
compatriots
so it was one of the turning points
including
in the in the japanese offensive
in the second world war
it was one of the turning points along
with the battle of infall in the battle
of kohima and the japanese
did lose these battles and that's where
the
string of defeats of the japanese army
began
so that is the furthest west the
japanese were able to come in asia and
from there they started getting defeated
and obviously with the japanese you also
had the involvement of the indian
national army
under the great sebastian ramos
so there is a memorial to the ina in
moirang
in manipur
which is about 50 or so kilometers south
of the city of imphal
so there is this wonderful museum there
and a memorial where you have these very
interesting photographs
of the ina and the records of the
of many manipuri civilians who fought
with the ina to get rid of the british
from indian soil
and all of this is forgotten history so
this this battle the the battle of red
hill was a terrible terrible battle very
bloody battle all the japanese died i
believe in that and that's why that hill
is called red hill so
i'm not sure if much of it is available
online the information but very
interesting question you ask and i'm
very surprised somebody even knows about
these things
so great great question
okay
okay let's take some
couple of more questions
who is more powerful
ias or the biggest businessman in india
the biggest businessman
are extremely wealthy
the ias is extremely powerful
power
money what is
more valuable
it's always power that is more valuable
so the business people
they have a lot of wealth and they can
translate some of that wealth into some
sort of power they can
buy favors if they need to and they have
a lot of influence
but the iis is the machinery the state
machinery that runs the entire
governance system of india
it can
an ias officer can destroy business if
he wants to he if he or she wants to
in the past it has been known to happen
at times
i'm sure many ias officers are really
brilliant people
really patriotic hard-working
well-meaning people but obviously there
are some who are not quite so good
some somewhere here and there a few
maybe possibly perhaps allegedly
so
who is more powerful ias or business
people it's the ias that holds all the
power
not the business people the business
people have a lot of money but no matter
how much money you have
the person who holds the
reins of the
machinery of the state is always more
powerful so is
is more powerful than
the richest business people
they just says how did indian ancestors
reach australia most likely they went by
by ships
india was always a maritime civilization
even in the rig veda there are mentions
in in the shabbat brahman etc there are
mentions of these enormous ships with a
hundred ores
so that is like several thousand years
ago and we know that the indian genetic
uh
imprint
in australia dates back to some about
five thousand years before today
so that is the the
time period of the saraswati hindu phase
of our civilization so at that time when
the saraswati hindu phase of of india
civilization was at more or less at its
peak
that's when
some
indian travelers sailors
most likely sailors they reached
australia and their genetic imprint is
still present there today so most likely
i mean if you look at the map let's go
to the map
so how do you reach australia either you
can go by land but you will have to
cross
the malacca strait
or the
so there is no direct land connection
so either you go by by hopping across
these islands of sumatra java and all
that or you go straight across the
the kalinga sagar which is now called
the bay of bengal and you go straight
down south australia
so it was clearly a sea voyage of some
kind
most likely in in ships so that's what
one can speculate happened obviously we
have found no material evidence of what
happened of of what ship they used or
whatever because it's been so long ago
but clearly our our people reached there
and left behind their genetic
evidence
right
um
uma says what will happen if uk repeals
india independence act i have no idea
there are some people who say that india
is still somehow
beholden to the uk in some ways the
there are some secret clauses in the
india independence act or something not
quite sure what the truth is
clearly something is fishy in all this
but i don't know but obviously even if
they repeal the india independence act
or whatever there's nothing they can
really do to change
to to to make india subservient to them
again they simply don't have the power
to do that
so
it would not really have make much of a
difference but it's it's interesting
because much of what's what happened
during the transfer of power has not
quite been revealed to the people of
india
okay let's take one more question
one more question
okay says what is justice
is justice revenge why does a perfect
judiciary system not exist today why are
loopholes present in all systems
what is justice justice means
well you can have a variety of
definitions of what justice is but
essentially justice means uh
righting the wrongs
r-i-g-h-t-i-n-g writing the wrongs if
somebody has done something wrong you
set it right according to whatever laws
you are following so that is justice
there is an element of revenge in it
but that revenge is for the sake of
deterrence
so you ensure by by
meeting out punishments
to the wrong doers you ensure that other
wrongdoers are deterred from doing that
that if i do this i'm going to be caught
and that the same thing will happen to
me
so there is an element of retribution
there is an element of deterrence to it
and there is an element of setting a
wrong right as well so if you
purchase a product and you don't get
what you expected you get a defective
product then obviously you deserve
compensation for that
and justice will ensure that you get the
compensation that the manufacturer or
the merchant who sold the product to you
will have to issue a refund to you or
something like that
so it's it's it's a complex thing and
why does a perfect judiciary system not
exist today i suspect a perfect
judiciary system never ever existed
anywhere in the world
because this is this is not mathematics
laws are man-made
or human-made creations
and there is no such thing as a perfect
law or perfect system of laws loopholes
are present in all systems that are
human made
and i don't think there was ever a
system of justice that was completely
100 infallible
and completely perfect so that's just
how it is and it's it's well known that
many people who are punished especially
in the u.s are punished wrong wrongfully
some people are are like
freed 20 30 after 20 30 years on death
row sometimes it happens and obviously
there have been people who have been
executed wrongly in the u.s and i'm sure
the same thing happens in all other
justice systems in the world including
perhaps in india as well perhaps perhaps
so yeah that's how it is
all right
what is the best parenting way should i
beat my child or not i would recommend
don't beat your child try and make the
child understand what what is right what
is wrong
beating
most likely would be counterproductive i
would say
i would say
so
please talk about kgf kolar gold fields
history of gold mining and wars fought
to acquire the gold mine i don't know
about this history i haven't seen the
movie i haven't studied the history
so i don't know but
sounds like an interesting topic i can
talk about the hira panda mines diamond
mines which the british
plundered
the word for diamond in hindi and most
indian languages is hera
that comes from the name of the mind
hira and panna
and today if you go to those mines
there's nothing there what happened the
british extracted everything of value
out of it so yeah that's what i can say
about that
and that brings us to the end of today's
session once again nearly two hours
thank you so much for all your questions
thank you for participating in this and
let's do the same thing next week and
hopefully i will
fix these
issues of the image quality
well thank you so much take care and i
will see you next week next episode
thank you bye